A Finding Aid to the Hiram Powers Papers, 1819-1953, bulk 1835-1883, in the Archives of American Art AAA.powehira
Archives of American Art
Hiram Powers papers
bulk 1835-1883
1819-1953
AAA.powehira
Archives of American Art
12.4 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Hiram Powers measure 12.4 linear feet and date from 1819 to 1953, with the bulk of the material dating from 1835 to 1883. Over two-thirds of the collection consists of Powers' correspondence with business associates, purchasers of his artwork, and numerous friends in the United States and Florence, Italy. Of note is Powers' "Studio Memorandum," from 1841 to 1845, which contains dated notations of letters written, receipts and expenditures, business contacts, works in progress, commissions and price quotations for work, comments on problems encountered during studio work, and other notes. Additional papers include scattered biographical material, financial and legal records, printed materials, photographs of Powers, his family, artwork, as well as an extensive collection of carte de visite and cabinet card portraits of many notable figures. Also found is a small amount of artwork by Powers and others, a scrapbook, and two autograph and memorabilia albums.
Powers, Hiram
facet
English; Italian
Provenance
The Hiram Powers papers were purchased by the Smithsonian American Art Museum in 1967 from Christina Seeber, great-granddaughter of Hiram Powers. A portion of these papers were loaned to the Archives of American Art for microfilming in 1974, and the entire collection was subsequently transferred to the archives from the museum in 1984.
Location of Originals
Copyprints of family photographs were donated in place of originals which were kept by Christina Seeber. Copyprints are available within the collection.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an unpublished manuscript entitled "White Marble: The Life and Letters of Hiram Powers, Sculptor," by Clara Louise Dentler, available on Archives of American Art microfilm reels 1102-1103. Microfilm reels 815-818 contain a "Collection of Letters from Old Residents of Cincinnati to Hiram Powers," compiled by Clara Louise Dentler, and loaned for microfilming by the Cincinnati Historical Society. These letters are not described in this finding aid. Microfilm reel 3416 contains copies of the Charles James Madison Eaton correspondence with Hiram Powers, and a letter received from Thomas Sully, 1845-1867, loaned by the Maryland Historical Society. Microfilm reel D117 contains "The Sculpture of Hiram Powers," by Paul B. Metzler, lent for microfilming by Ohio State University. Additional Hiram Powers papers are available at the Winterthur Museum.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Hiram Powers in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2007, and total 26858 images.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
American sculptor Hiram Powers (1805-1873) was born in Woodstock, Vermont, and lived and worked briefly in Washington, D.C. and Boston, before settling permanently in Florence, Italy. Powers is known for portrait busts of prominent American politicians and his idealized neo-classical sculptures, most notably the Greek Slave.
The second youngest of nine children, Powers moved with his family to Cincinnati, Ohio in 1817. When he was 18 he began working in a factory that repaired watches and organs, and he later worked in the mechanical department of Dorfeuille's Western Museum. There, he developed his interest in sculpture and received a commission to create wax figures for a tableau of Dante's Inferno. In 1825 he studied with the Prussian sculptor Frederick Eckstein, who taught him how to model clay and make plaster casts. His early commissions for portrait busts caught the attention of Nicholas Longworth, who became his first patron and funded his travel to Washington, DC, in 1834. While in Washington, Powers completed portrait busts of several prominent politicians, including President Andrew Jackson. He also briefly worked on several commissions in Boston. In 1837, thanks to the patronage of Colonel John S. Preston, he and his family moved to Florence, Italy. He intended to live there for only a few years, but remained there for the rest of his life.
Powers set up a studio in Florence with several assistants, and continued to work on portrait bust commissions. He and his family were active members of the intellectual community of American and English émigrés, such as Robert and Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Horatio Greenough, the Trollope family, and many others. His studio was also a frequent stop on tourists' visits to Florence. In 1839 Powers began working on idealized sculptures in the Neo-classical style, based on history, mythology, and religion. Perhaps most famous of these are Greek Slave and Fisher Boy. Completed in 1845, Greek Slave was exhibited in London and toured the United States. The sculpture received wide attention from the press for its depiction of female nudity and its philosophical significance, and established Powers' international success as a sculptor.
During his career Powers received private and government commissions for portrait busts and ideal sculptures, and sold many replicas of his work. He also invented improved tools for use in his studio, which were patented in the United States, and he developed a special finishing process for marble from the Carrara quarry. He maintained friendships with many Americans through extensive correspondence, and openly expressed his views on the Civil War and the abolition of slavery. Powers' son Longworth had a photography and sculpture studio nearby, and his son Preston, also a sculptor, took over many of Hiram Powers' remaining projects at the time of his death in 1873.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor Hiram Powers measure 12.4 linear feet and date from 1819 to 1953, with the bulk of the material dating from 1835 to 1883. Over two-thirds of the collection consists of Powers' correspondence, which is particularly rich in documenting his artwork, methodology, and his interaction with business associates, purchasers of his artwork, and his numerous friends in the United States and Florence, Italy. Other papers include scattered biographical material, writings by Powers and others, financial and legal records, news clippings and printed items, photographs of Powers, his family, artwork, as well as an extensive collection of carte de visite and cabinet card portraits of many notable figures. Also found is a small amount of artwork by Powers and others, a scrapbook, and two autograph and memorabilia albums.
Biographical material consists of documents for honors conferred on Powers, price lists and inventories of his artwork, papers regarding his death, including a translation of his will, and ephemera, such as his studio cap.
The bulk of the collection consists of Powers' correspondence with family, friends, business associates, and others, documenting his career as an artist and his personal life after he and his family moved to Florence, Italy, in 1837. Almost all of the letters have typed unconfirmed transcriptions completed by volunteers at the Smithsonian American Art Museum. Besides details of his studio work and business dealings, his letters often discuss his views on aesthetics, American politics, slavery and the Civil War, and Spiritualism. Notable correspondence is with William B. Astor, Edward Everett, Samuel York Atlee, William and E. Clementine Kinney, George P. Marsh, George Peabody, Presidents Andrew Jackson and John Quincy Adams, William Cullen Bryant, Elizabeth Barrett Browning, John C. Calhoun, Thomas Crawford, John A. Dix, Asher Durand, Charles Francis Fuller, Henry Peters Gray, Horace Greeley, George P. A. Healy, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Samuel F. B. Morse, W. W. Story, John Sartain, Frances Trollope, and Daniel Webster.
Writings by Powers include his "Studio Memorandum," a journal-type notebook he kept from 1841 to 1845, which contains dated notations of letters written, receipts and expenditures, business contacts, works in progress, commissions and price quotations for work, comments on problems encountered during studio work, and other notes. Additional writings include poetry and autobiographical essays and instructions for handling his sculptures. Writings by others include poetry, most of which was written in praise of Powers' artwork. Of note are handwritten transcripts of poems by Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Bayard Taylor, and John Quincy Adams. Also found here are short writings about Powers and his artwork.
Scattered financial and legal records in this collection include patent documents for tools invented by Powers, legal agreements, account statements, and bills and receipts. Printed material consists of news clippings, two booklets, an art association brochure, and an exhibition catalog for works by Powers.
This collection contains photographs of Hiram Powers, his family, friends, notable public figures, and artwork. Many of the photographs were taken by his son, Longworth Powers, who had a private photography studio in Florence. Included are portraits of Powers and his family, as well as a collection of 267 carte de visite and cabinet card portraits of artists, performers, politicians, writers, scientists, and other public figures, many of whom were friends with the Powers family. Other photographs depict Woodstock, Vermont, the marble quarry at Carrara, Italy, and artwork by Hiram and Preston Powers. Also found here is a photograph album kept by Louisa Powers.
Artwork consists of three drawings by Hiram Powers, including a caricature of Miner Kellogg. Also found in this collection is a scrapbook containing news clippings regarding the American tour of the sculpture Greek Slave, an autograph album belonging to Louisa Powers, and an album containing pencil drawings by Preston Powers and dried flowers collected on travels.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1841-1927 (Box 1, 15; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1819-1883 (Box 1-10; 9.0 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1827-1887 (Box 10; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Financial and Legal Records, circa 1840s-1892, 1915 (Box 10, OV 17; 8 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1845-1953 (Box 10; 5 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1860s-1900, 1927, 1932 (Box 10-13, 16, OV 17; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, 1860, mid-1800s (Box 11; 4 folders)
Series 8: Scrapbooks and Albums, 1847-1876 (Box 14; 3 folders)
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Astor, William B. (William Backhouse), 1792-1875; Atlee, Samuel Yorke, b. 1808; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Crawford, Thomas, 1813 or 14-1857; Dix, John A. (John Adams), 1798-1879; Durand, Asher Brown, 1796-1886; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Fuller, Charles Francis; Gray, Henry Peters, 1819-1877; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872; Healy, G.P.A. (George Peter Alexander), 1813-1894; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Kinney, E. Clementine; Kinney, William; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Marsh, George Perkins, 1801-1882; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Peabody, George, 1795-1869; Powers, Longworth, 1835-1904; Powers, Preston, b. 1843; Sartain, John, 1808-1897; Story, William Wetmore, 1819-1895; Taylor, Bayard, 1825-1878; Trollope, Francis; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Drawings; Photographs; Poetry; Scrapbooks; Sculptors--Italy--Florence; Writings
- Biographical Material, 1841-1927; Series 1; (Box 1, 15; 0.8 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains scattered biographical material documenting the life and career of Hiram Powers. Included is a brief, incomplete, handwritten list of births, marriages, and deaths in the Powers family. Also found are several documents for honors conferred on Hiram Powers such as honorary degrees, membership into art organizations, including the National Academy of Design, and an appointment by the U. S. Government as a commercial agent in Florence. Many of these documents are in Italian. This series also contains several price lists and inventories of artwork by Hiram Powers, including a studio inventory from 1905, and lists of works done by his chief carver, Remigio Peschi. Also found are documents regarding Powers' death, such as obituaries, death notices, a handwritten copy of a funeral address, and a bound document entitled "Translation of Hiram Powers Will". This document was written by George and Mrs. Marsh, and includes a copy of Powers' will, notes about his estate, notes regarding family disputes and legal matters, and copies of family letters regarding the estate. Also found here are scattered items belonging to Powers, such as his studio cap and a handkerchief.
  Arrangement note
  Items are arranged chronologically within each folder. This series has been scanned in its entirety except for the handkerchief and studio cap.
  - List of Powers Family Births, Marriages, and Deaths, circa 1871 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Honors Conferred to Hiram Powers, 1841-1873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Price Lists of Works by Hiram Powers, 1872-circa late-1800s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lists of Artworks by Hiram Powers, circa 1870s-1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of Work done by Remigio Peschi, circa 1877 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Death Notices and Funeral Reading for Hiram Powers, 1873-1874 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Translation of Hiram Powers Will,", circa 1883 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Translation of Hiram Powers Will," Typescript, circa 1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inventory, "Mama's & Papa's property still remaining in Uncle Longworth's studio,", 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Bronze Plaque for Work by Powers,", circa mid-1800s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tag for Hiram Powers' Walking Stick, circa 1870s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ticket of Admission, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hiram Powers Studio Cap, circa 1850s-1873; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Handkerchief, circa mid-1800s; (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1819-1883; Series 2; (Box 1-10; 9.0 linear feet)
  This series contains 9.0 linear feet of correspondence between Hiram Powers and family, friends, business associates, and others, primarily documenting his career and personal life after he and his family moved to Florence, Italy, in 1837. Found here are thousands of incoming letters as well as copies of outgoing letters written by Powers. Outgoing letters were copied by a process of placing moistened paper in a press, and because of this, these letters are often difficult to read and very fragile. Some of the personal correspondence is addressed to both Powers and his wife Elizabeth, or just to Elizabeth, and much of the business correspondence from the 1870s, while Hiram Powers was in ill health, was written by or addressed to his son, Preston Powers. Almost all letters have typed transcriptions completed by volunteers at the Smithsonian American Art Museum before the collection was donated to the Archives of American Art. Researchers should note that archivists have not verified these transcripts for accuracy.
  Correspondence in this collection reveals much about Hiram Powers' artwork, methodology, and his interaction with business associates, patrons, and purchasers of his artwork. His business correspondence is with patrons such as William B. Astor, Edwin C. Litchfield, and John S. Preston, his business agents, such as Theodore Dehon in New York and M. M. Holloway in London, banking firms and shipping companies, and committees for U. S. government commissions. These letters often discuss financial details, his progress on commissioned sculptures, shipping instructions, his tool inventions and patent applications, and legal issues. Powers also corresponded with numerous individuals who privately commissioned works or inquired on purchasing works.
  Powers and his family maintained a large circle of friends in the United States and Europe, including many artists, writers, as well as politicians whom he met while working in Washington, DC. In his very detailed letters he discusses his artwork and current studio projects, his views on the art world, the art community in Florence, ideal sculpture, and aesthetics. He also shares his thoughts on American politics, abolition of slavery and the Civil War, and Spiritualism. Letters sent to Powers from friends and acquaintances discuss general news of family, friends, travels, invitations, and inquiries on studying with Powers. Also found are many letters of introduction for people wishing to visit his studio in Florence. Powers corresponded extensively with family members, including his brothers Benjamin and Sampson Powers, and his wife, Elizabeth, during the period that he lived in Washington, DC.
  Also of note in this series is extensive correspondence with his close friends Edward Everett, Samuel York Atlee, Sidney Brooks, William and E. Clementine Kinney, George P. Marsh, George Peabody, and John P. Richardson. Other notable correspondence includes letters to Powers from Presidents Andrew Jackson and John Quincy Adams, and letters to or from William Cullen Bryant, Elizabeth Barrett Browning, John C. Calhoun, Thomas Crawford, Samuel Colt, John A. Dix, Asher Durand, Charles Francis Fuller, Henry Peters Gray, Horace Greeley, George P. A. Healy, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, William Morris, Samuel F. B. Morse, Edmund Niemann, W. W. Story, John Sartain, Frances Trollope, and Daniel Webster.
  Letters have been arranged alphabetically. Letters from individuals who had correspondence with Powers of four letters or less are found within the miscellaneous folders. This series has been scanned in its entirety, including the transcripts.
  - Adams, Henry J. and Abigail Gibson Adams, 1850-1861; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Amory, James S., 1839-1870 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ashton, Thomas B., circa 1847-1852 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Aspinwall, William H., 1850-1867 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Astor, J. J. (John Jacob), 1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Astor, William B., 1855-1861 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Atlee, Samuel York, 1845-1871; (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-25)
  - Austin, Charles L., 1844-1848, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Austin, Frances L., circa 1848-1873; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - A, Miscellaneous: Aa-Ak, 1847-1883 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    A. & A. Lawrence & Co.
    Abbot, Elizabeth
    Abbot, Wyllys S.
    Abert, James W.
    Acworth, N. N.
    Adams, Anna G.
    Adams, F. G.
    Adams, John Quincy
    Addington, H. U.
    Akers, Paul
  - A, Miscellaneous: Al-Am, 1838-1873 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Alexander, Francis
    Alexander, L. G.
    Alexander, Walter S.
    Allen, J. Prentiss
    Allen, William E.
    Almonde, Luigi
    Alward, Dennis R.
    Ames, Jas. T.
    Ammen, Daniel
  - A, Miscellaneous: An-Ar, 1841-1872 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Anderson, Charles
    Anderson, E. M. C.
    Andrews, Joseph
    Andrews, Sarah G.
    Angel, B. F.
    Appleby Bros.
    Armstrong, J. S.
    Arnold, Stephen H.
  - A, Miscellaneous: As-Av, 1838-1876 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Ashhurst, Richard
    Astor, P. W.
    Atchison, S. R.
    Atkinson, J. Beauvington
    Austin, Edwin
    Austin, J. E.
    Austin, James T.
    Avery, Charles L.
  - Baker, Richard, 1863-1868 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baldwin, Isaac, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ball, Mr., 1868 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Baring Brothers & Co., 1850-1872 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bayley, John Clowes, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Bellows, Henry W., 1868-1870 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bennett, M. C. B., circa 1841-1846 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Binda, Joseph A., 1845-1858 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bishop, Thomas, 1852-1868 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Bisshopp, M. A. (Lady), 1849-1850 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Bolton, A. I., 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bonnin, William, 1846-1859 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bosson, Thomas M., 1835-1840 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Bosson, William, 1831-1873 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Brewer, Gardner, 1865-1868 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Bridge, Horatio & Mrs. C. M. Bridge, circa 1848-1855 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Brooks, Sidney, 1843-1852; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-53)
  - Brooks, Sidney, 1853-1856; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 54-57)
  - Brooks, Sidney, 1857-1860; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Brooks, Sidney, 1861-1863; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Brooks, Sidney, 1864-1867; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
  - Brooks, Sidney, 1868-1873; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
  - Brooks, Sidney, Undated Letters, circa 1843-1873 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bross, William, 1867-1870 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bryant, William C., 1850-1871 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bryson, P. M., 1859-1860 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Burns, Walter H., 1866-1868 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Burrows, Philip, 1855-1862 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bag-Ban, 1851-1870 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Bagot, C. E.
    Bailey, I. S.
    Bailey & Son
    Baker, T. F.
    Balestier, J.
    Bamps, F. A.
    Bancroft, Mr.
    Banta, Weart
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bar-Bay, 1839-1867 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Barclay, R.
    Barlow, John
    Barnard, Jas. M.
    Barnum, Mrs. Zenus
    Bartlett, Mr.
    Barton, Jno. M.
    Baruch, Maurice
    Bates, Joshua C.
    Bayley, T. I.
  - B, Miscellaneous: Be, 1840-1866 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Bebb, E. R.
    Beckwith, N. M.
    Belden, Edwin F.
    Bennett, D. W. B.
    Benton, F. D.
    Berney, George D.
    Berry, N.
    Bessey, Solon
    Betty, Joseph
    Bevan, Will
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bi, 1850-1870 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Bielle, Comte de
    Bierstadt, Mr.
    Bigelow, E. B.
    Bininger, Abraham
    Birchard, M. W.
    Bishop, C. A.
    Bissell, L. B.
    Bittinger, Edmund C.
    Bixby, Jno. M.
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bl, 1851-1862 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Blafield, John
    Blair, Will T.
    Blake, G. S.
    Blake, Oscar F.
    Bliss, Ira
    Blogden, Mrs.
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bo, 1835-1873 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Boccella, Madam
    Bossange, Hector
    Bosson, C. T.
    Boulden, James E. P.
    Boulware, William
    Bowles, William B.
    Bowman, J.
    Boyd, James R.
    Boyd, Mrs.
    Bozzanti, Mr.
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bra-Bri, 1840-1869 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Bracebridge, C. Holte[?]
    Brackett, E. M.
    Bradburn, G.
    Braine, George N.
    Brand, Frederick B.
    Brassus, M.
    Bravo, Gio.
    Bray, W. B.
    Brent, Henry J.
    Breese, Mr.
    Brewster, C. S.
    Bridges, Charles
    Brigham, Charles H.
    Brimmer, M.
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bro, 1844-1871 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Broadfield, E. J.
    Broadhead, J. R.
    Bronson, David
    Brooks, Fanny
    Brooks, Peter C.
    Brown, Frederick L.
    Brown, J. B.
    Brown, J. H.
    Brown, John
    Browne, J. Ross
    Browning, Elizabeth Barrett
  - B, Miscellaneous: Bu, 1847-1866 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Buffum, W. A.
    Buonarroti, Rosina
    Burchard, M. W.
    Burguyn, Mrs.
    Burke, G.
    Burnett, George W.
    Burns, George
    Burt, J. Otis
    Burton, Ira M.
    Butler, E. S.
    Butler, H.
    Butler, William Allen
  - Calvert, George H., circa 1848-1865; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Cameron, James, 1846-1856 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Carbonel, E., 1850-1851 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Casselli, Lodovico, 1857-1863 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Cassels, Walter H., 1868-1869 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Chamberlain, William L., 1865-1866 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Chanler, John & Elizabeth, circa 1850-1853 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Childe, E. V., 1840-1856 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Cholmondely, Reginald, circa 1865 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Clark, Charles H., 1870-1873; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 45-47)
  - Clarke, J. Edwards, 1839-1881; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 48-51)
  - Cogdell, John Stephen, 1843-1847 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Cohen, Solomon, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Collie, Alexander, 1854-1863 (Box 2, Folder 54)